A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Economic Opportunity and Assets Program, Vice President, Office Files of Pablo Farias FA1358
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Economic Opportunity and Assets Program, Vice President, Office Files of Pablo Farias
1954-2014
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Farias, Pablo
FA1358
9.21 Cubic Feet 24 document boxes: 23 letter size and 1 legal size
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of five series.
Original order was maintained as much as possible.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Leadership for a Changing World, 1995-2006
Series 2. Meetings and trips files, 2001-2012
Series 3. Field Office administration, 1975-2011
Series 4. General files, 1954-2014
Series 5. Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) Unit files, 2005-2013
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in two accessions in 2021 and 2022 and was ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2021:102 and 2022:055.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the office files of Pablo Farias who worked at the Ford Foundation for more than a decade, primarily in the Foundation's assets building programs. Farias served as Deputy Vice President and Vice President of the Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) and then Vice President of the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) after an organizational restructuring at the Foundation. Prior to his work in the assets programs, Farias served as the Foundation's Representative for Mexico and Central America and was based in the Mexico City Office. The collection does not contain any files created from Farias' time as Representative for Mexico.
There are several different groupings of materials within the collection that are represented by different series. The first series pertains to the Leadership for a Changing World program, the second series contains files documenting meetings and trips, and the third series contains files documenting the administration of the Foundation's various field offices. The fourth series has been labeled general files because it contains a mix of meeting and trip files, programs strategy files, administrative files, and subject files. The last series contains a group of files that are specifically about the different program units of the EOA.
Within the collection, there are not clear divisions between materials Farias created when he worked in ASSETS and materials created when he worked in EOA. The collection also includes materials created before Farias started working in the Foundation's assets programs and materials created after he left the Foundation. The records created prior to Farias' tenure in ASSETS appear to have been created by Melvin Oliver, Farias' predecessor as Vice President of ASSETS, and the records created after Farias left the Foundation may have been created by his successor as EOA Vice President, Xavier de Souza Briggs. The collection is more like the office files of the Vice President for the Foundation's assets building programs, from ASSETS to EOA, than files specific to Farias' work.
The collection's contents show program interests and strategy history of the Foundation's assets building programs. These interests include sustainable economic development in consideration of environment and climate change concerns and financial asset building support for low-income communities and countries in the Global South. Files document the emphasis of HIV/AIDS, reproductive health, and sexuality in the Foundation's international programming. Relief and recovery for natural disasters was also a focus of the Foundation in the mid-2000s in response to the 2004 Indian Ocean earthquake and tsunami and Hurricane Katrina's impact on the Gulf Coast of the United States in 2005. Materials concerning program strategy discuss organizational learning, initiative evaluation, and lines of work statements.
Briefing books are one of the most prevalent types of materials found throughout the collection. These records document the subject matter, context, and scheduling of various meetings, site visits, and projects. Other common material formats found throughout the collection include correspondence, drafts, notes, reports, presentations, agendas, itineraries, articles, newsclips, publications, and Recommended Grant Action records (RGAs). There are also a few photographs and digital media items in the collection. The photographs document trips to different countries.
Ford Foundation; Africa; Asia; Latin America; Community development; Conservation of natural resources; Disaster relief; Economic development; Financial security; HIV (Viruses); Leadership; Reproductive health; Social forestry programs; Sustainable development; Photographs
- Leadership for a Changing World, 1995-2006; 1; 1.05 Cubic Feet 2.75 letter size boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains files concerning the Ford Foundation's Leadership for a Changing World Program (LCW). Ford managed the LCW in partnership with the Advocacy Institute and the Robert F. Wagner Graduate School of Public Service at New York University. LCW recognized and supported community leaders and promoted leadership development.
  Files document proposals for the program, press coverage, awardees, and assessment of the program.
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW) - Strategic communications, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW) - 2001 and 2002 Awardees and Colleagues photographs, circa 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    File contains three still images. The images are photographs of the 2001 and 2002 Leadership for a Changing World (LCW) Awardees and Colleagues.
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW) May 10, 2006 meeting (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW) Final Evaluation, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW) - Research Center for Leadership in Action (RCLA), 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW), 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Seeking the Common Values of Successful Social Change Leadership: A Co-Operative Inquiry, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Open for research. Digital access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW), 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW) - New York University Wagner School proposal, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW), 2001-2005 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - A World of Possibilities: A Mainstream Media Project Radio Production - Media Metamorphosis: Trance of Transformation, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW) - Finalists descriptions and recent awardees controversy, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW), 2005 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LWC) - Advocacy Institute, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Leadership for a Changing World (LCW), 1995-2006 (Box 3, Folder 15-18)
- Meetings and trips files, 2001-2012; 2; 1.8 Cubic Feet 4.5 document boxes: 3.5 letter size and 1 legal size
  This series contains meeting and trip files Pablo Farias created when he served as Vice President of the Ford Foundation's Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) and then Vice President of the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA). These meetings and trips include internal Ford Foundation meetings, grantee site visits, trips to Ford Foundation field offices, and meetings and conferences related to program interests.
  Many of the field office visits and international trips documented in the series were organized for Farias and other senior Foundation staff like President Luis Ubinas. Several files in the series show the Foundation's support for community forestry as a route towards sustainable economic development while other meetings and trips show the focus of HIV/AIDS in the Foundation's international programming.
  There are other files related to meetings and trips found throughout the rest of the collection, but the meeting and trips files in this series were specifically stored together. The collection arrangement thus reflects that.
  - ASPIRE (America Saving for Personal Investment, Retirement, and Education) briefing, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania - People for People (PFP), circa 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Fannie Mae/Self-Help - Community Action Program (CAP) Press Conference, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Institute for Social Change Across Borders June 2004 meeting, Los Angeles, California (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Ford Foundation 2004 All Africa Program Staff Meeting, Johannesburg, South Africa (Box 4, Folder 22-23)
  - Chicago Global Donors Network 2nd Annual Conference on International Giving, Chicago, Illinois, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Ford Foundation Hanoi, Vietnam Office November 2004 visit (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Camden Regional Equity Demonstration January 2005 site visit, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 26-28)
  - ASPIRE (America Saving for Personal Investment, Retirement, and Education) press conference, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania - People for People (PFP) site visit, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Global Round Table on Climate Change, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Strategic Partnership Retreat (community forestry) May 2005, Tarrytown, New York (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - PolicyLink - Advancing Regional Equity Summit, May 23, 2005, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Vancouver, Canada, May 2005 - Community forestry, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - China August 2005 visit, circa 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - China August 2005 visit, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Beijing and Guilin, China Ford Foundation Trustees August 2005 visit (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Benq CD, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Introduction to Grassroots Environmental NGOs in China, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Kenya August 2005 visit, 2001-2005 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Indonesia December 2004 visit (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - TrustAfrica - Ford Foundation senior staff visit, February 2007, Dakar, Senegal, 2006-2007 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Indonesia April 2006 visit (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Ford Foundation All Africa Program Staff Meeting, May 2006, Nairobi, Kenya (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Ford Foundation All Africa Program Staff Meeting, September 2007, Cairo and Alexandria, Egypt (Box 6, Folder 42-43)
  - Rural Livelihoods Practitioners Learning Group (RLPLG) and Ford Foundation Affinity Group on Development Finance (AGDF) meetings, October 2007, Astoria, Oregon, part 1 (Box 6, Folder 44-45)
  - Rural Livelihoods Practitioners Learning Group (RLPLG) and Ford Foundation Affinity Group on Development Finance (AGDF) meetings, October 2007, Astoria, Oregon, part 2 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Meeting on Population and Reproductive Health, January 2008, Seattle, Washington, 2007-2008 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Ford Foundation Sexuality and Reproductive Health (SRH) Learning Meeting and Global HIV Initiative Learning Exchange, 2008, South Africa, 2005-2008 (Box 7, Folder 48-49)
  - South Africa and Mozambique April 2008 visit (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Ford Foundation September 2008 Cleveland Site Visit (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - West Africa 2009 visit (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Open Society Institute Donors Meeting, February 2009, Dakar, Senegal (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - November 2009 visit to Jakarta, Indonesia Office with Ford Foundation President Luis Ubinas, 2008-2009 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - March 2010 site visit to India with Ford Foundation President Luis Ubinas (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - March 2012 Trip to Indonesia and India - Asia Rep Rap Meeting (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Indonesia 2012 visit (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Sex Worker Education and Advocacy Taskforce (SWEAT) safe sex education pamphlets, undated (Box 8, Folder 58)
- Field Office administration, 1975-2011; 3; 1.05 Cubic Feet 2.75 letter size boxes
  Files in this series pertain to the administration and activities of various Ford Foundation field offices.
  Administrative concerns documented within the files include office operations like staffing, policies, and office building matters. The series provides some insight into the history of the Ford Foundation's international offices structuring such as the transfer of Thailand programming to the Hanoi, Vietnam Office and the closing of the Manila, Philippines Office.
  Files also show how the programming interests of the Foundation's assets programs were carried out in different regions of the world through the field offices. Such interests include sustainable development through community forestry and other natural resource conservation means in Asia, Africa, and Latin America, support for disaster recovery in response to the 2004 Indian Ocean earthquake and tsunami in South and Southeast Asia and Eastern Africa, and HIV/AIDS throughout various regions.
  The last part of the series was separated from the rest of the files prior to transfer to the RAC. The intellectual relationship between the materials was reestablished during processing.
  - Rio de Janeiro, Brazil Office, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Santiago, Chile Office, 1995-2008 (Box 8, Folder 60-61)
  - Beijing, China Office - Beijing Normal University (BNU) One Foundation Philanthropy Research Institute delegation, 2010-2011 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Beijing, China Office, part 1, 1999-2010 (Box 8, Folder 63-64)
  - Beijing, China Office, part 2, 1999-2007 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Cairo, Egypt Office, 1997-2008 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - New Delhi, India Office, 1975-2009 (Box 9, Folder 67-68)
  - Tata Relief Committee - Tsunami Relief Work, undated (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Jakarta, Indonesia Office, 1996-2011 (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - Nairobi, Kenya Office, 1996-2005 (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - Mexico City, Mexico Office, 1999-2010 (Box 10, Folder 71)
  - Lagos, Nigeria Office - Lagos Office 50th Anniversary, 2010 (Box 10, Folder 72)
  - Lagos, Nigeria Office, 2000-2002 (Box 10, Folder 73)
  - Manila, Philippines Office, 1997-2002 (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - Moscow, Russia Office, 1996-2001 (Box 10, Folder 75)
  - Johannesburg, South Africa Office, 1995-2005 (Box 22, Folder 213)
  - Johannesburg, South Africa Office - John Gerhart memos, 1996-1998 (Box 22, Folder 214)
  - Hanoi, Vietnam Office, 1997-2003 (Box 22, Folder 215-216)
  - Hanoi, Vietnam Office - Asset building, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 217)
  - Hanoi, Vietnam Office - John Ambler memos, closing the Bangkok, Thailand Office, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 218)
  - Hanoi, Vietnam Office - Gary Suwannarat memos, Thailand environment and culture, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 219)
- General files, 1954-2014; 4; 4.56 Cubic Feet 12 letter size boxes
  This series contains an assortment of different types of files created and maintained by Pablo Farias. These types of files include meeting and trip files, administrative files, subject files, and program strategy files. The different files were stored together, so it was decided during processing to keep them in the same series. As mentioned in the collection scope and content note, there are materials created before Farias started working in the Foundation's assets building programs and materials created after Farias left the Ford Foundation.
  Like in the second series, meeting and trip files encompass internal Foundation meetings, grantee site visits, trips to Foundation field offices in countries outside the United States, and conferences and meetings related to assets programing interests. Several files concerning trips to Foundation field offices are more broadly focused and contain materials related to more than one visit as well as materials related to that office's program strategy and activities for its region. One file includes a large number of images captured during visits to China and India in 2005 and 2007.
  A significant segment of the program strategy materials in the series concern initiative strategy, evaluation, and impact. These records show the Foundation's broader efforts to embed organizational learning. Many of these records were produced after Farias left the Foundation.
  - Economic development - Affinity Group on Development Finance (AGDF), 2004 (Box 10, Folder 76)
  - Economic development - Affinity Group on Development Finance (AGDF) 2003 Meeting, Portland, Maine (Box 10, Folder 77)
  - Economic development - Affinity Group on Development Finance (AGDF) 2003 Meeting, Portland, Maine reading materials (Box 10, Folder 78)
  - Economic development - Consultative Group to Assist the Poor (CGAP) Phase III Strategy, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - Communications - Ford Foundation Website, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 80)
  - Communications - Affinity Group on Development Finance (AGDF) publication, 2002-2004 (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - Communications - Communication strategy, 2004 April 23 (Box 10, Folder 82)
  - Communications - Publications, undated (Box 10, Folder 83)
  - Communications - Communications review, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 84)
  - Communications - Ford Foundation Office of the President communications, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 85)
  - Conservation NGOs and communities, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 86)
  - Florida International University (FIU) Cuban Research Institute (CRI), 1992-2006 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - Indigenous peoples, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 88)
  - Community and Resource Development (CRD), 2012 (Box 10, Folder 89)
  - DVP monthly review, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 90)
  - Office - Grants and affinity groups, 2002-2003 (Box 10, Folder 91)
  - Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) Transition Review, undated (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - Vector III Task Force, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 93)
  - Sanlaap – Grant No. 1045-0966, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 94)
  - Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) Learning Group Activities - Learning Tools Status Report, 2003-2004 (Box 11, Folder 95)
  - The Twenty-First Century Foundation – Grounding Roots and Forming Partnerships, 2003 May (Box 11, Folder 96)
  - The Just City, undated (Box 11, Folder 97)
  - Center for Advocacy and Research (CFAR), 2007 February 5 (Box 11, Folder 98)
  - Pablo Farias notes, undated (Box 11, Folder 99)
  - Program Officer Memo guidelines, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 100)
  - Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) - Communications Workshop and Speech Coaching, 2012 (Box 11, Folder 101)
  - Visits to Jakarta, Indonesia Office and Indonesia program strategy, 2006-2010 (Box 11, Folder 102)
  - Rural Economic Research Group of the State Council Development Research Center - Survey Research on Improving Grassland Ecological Recovery Policies, 2009-2010 (Box 11, Folder 103)
  - Poverty Alleviation Strategy - Environmentally friendly poverty reduction, undated (Box 11, Folder 104)
  - Visits to Beijing, China Office and China program strategy, 2007-2010 (Box 11, Folder 105-106)
  - Coordenacao Das Organizacoes Indigenas da Amazonia Brazileria certificate, 2008 June 2 (Box 11, Folder 107)
  - Building Economic Security over a Lifetime, March 2011, Ford Foundation Grantee Convening (Box 11, Folder 108)
  - Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) Ford Foundation Trustee Committee March 2011 site visit to Chicago, Illinois and Washington, D.C. (Box 11, Folder 109)
  - Ford Foundation Gulf Coast Region Ford Foundation Trustee April 2007 visit - Recommended Grant Actions (Box 12, Folder 110)
  - Program Leadership Meeting, September 2009, New York City, New York (Box 12, Folder 111)
  - Luis Ubinas memo – Roger Kennedy's Thoughts on Financial Management, 2009 (Box 12, Folder 112)
  - Ford Foundation Strategy to Expand Civil Society Engagement in Support of the Rio Plus20 Conference on Sustainable Development, undated (Box 12, Folder 113)
  - Centre for Policy Research (CPR) - The Ford Foundation and India: The Urban Sector, 2009 (Box 12, Folder 114)
  - National Consultation Workshop on "Project" - Urban India Reform Observatory (UIRO), 2009 (Box 12, Folder 115)
  - Ford Foundation Latin America Regional Meeting, March 15, 2007, Antigua, Guatemala (Box 12, Folder 116)
  - November 2009 visit to New Delhi, India Office (Box 12, Folder 117)
  - Living Cities November 2009 meeting – Looking Forward (Box 12, Folder 118)
  - Research and Advanced Training Grant to Harvard University Graduate School of Business Administration, 1954-1966 (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - Housing – Indonesia, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Housing Program Display, undated (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Progress Report – Revitalization of Traditional Cemeti Art House, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Progress Report – Housing Reconstruction and Rehabilitation Program in Klisat, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Dokumentasi Kegiatan, undated (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Community and Resource Development (CRD) - Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) 2006 trip to the Amazon (Brazil) report (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - Ford Foundation Bay Area April 2009 visit - Progress and Promise for Developments (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - Visiting Representatives of Ford Foundation to Ilisan Community Bank Limited, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - BRIDGE Housing - Background/Context of West Oakland, California, undated (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - NCB Capital Impact – Shared Equity Home Ownership, undated (Box 12, Folder 125)
  - Ford Foundation Africa programming, 2006-2007 (Box 12, Folder 126)
  - Wassan - Field Visit to Mulkalapally, Nalgonda, India, undated (Box 12, Folder 127)
  - Presentation and Discussion Session on Science and Policy Nexus, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 128)
  - Ford Foundation Board Chair Kathryn Fuller and President Luis Ubinas December 2007 visit to Mexico City, Mexico Office (Box 12, Folder 129)
  - Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) Overview, circa 2008-2009 (Box 13, Folder 130)
  - Tsunami response - Indonesia, 2004-2006 (Box 13, Folder 131)
  - Brookings Institution/Ford Foundation workshop - Asset-Based Approaches to Poverty Reduction in a Globalized Context, June 2006, Washington D.C., 2005-2006 (Box 13, Folder 132)
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees January 2006 Meeting - Latin America Regional Program (Box 13, Folder 133)
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees January 2006 Meeting – Guest speaker, Michael Shifter (Box 13, Folder 134)
  - Building the Community Development Field: Origins and Growth of Intermediary Organizations, Tom Seessel, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 135)
  - Ford Foundation Trustees 2007 visit to Mexico City, Mexico Office (Box 13, Folder 136)
  - Ford Foundation Trustees 2007 visit to Mexico City, Mexico Office - Mexico Security Study Group (Box 13, Folder 137)
  - Ford Foundation Trustees 2007 visit to Mexico City, Mexico Office, circa 2005-2007 (Box 13, Folder 138)
  - Visits to Beijing, China Office and China program strategy, 2001-2009 (Box 13, Folder 139)
  - Visits to Beijing, China Office and China program strategy - March 2007 Beijing trip (Box 13, Folder 140)
  - Heyang County - Kate Hartford, 2005-2006 (Box 13, Folder 140)
  - Visits to New Delhi, India Office and India program strategy, 2004-2008 (Box 14, Folder 141-142)